so we're continuing looking at examples
of spinners in physics in the last video
we introduced Jones vectors for
representing the polarizations of
electromagnetic waves the top component
gives the magnitude and phase of a
horizontally polarized wave and the
bottom component gives the magnitude and
phase of a vertically polarized wave
by combining these two polarizations in
different amounts and phases we can get
other polarizations like diagonal
anti-diagonal left circular and right
circular polarizations
in this video we're going to find that
we can rotate between all these
polarizations by using special matrices
called su2 matrices and this will reveal
how there's an angle doubling
relationship between physical space and
wave polarizations
this will show us that Jones vectors are
actually spinners
so when it comes to light waves in real
life we can manipulate the polarization
of light waves using various optical
devices like polarizers and wave plates
in the world of math these correspond to
multiplying our Jones vectors by various
matrices called Jones matrices
I'm not going to discuss polarizers in
this video minute physics and three blue
one brown have already done really good
videos on polarizers that I've Linked In
the description
for this video the more relevant Optical
device I'm going to talk about is the
wave plate
a wave plate is a device that
essentially rotates one polarization
into another by introducing phase delays
you probably already know that a light
wave will change speed when it passes
from one medium to another such as
passing from air into a crystal
because of the change in speed by the
time the light exits the crystal there
is a phase change in the resulting wave
compared to light that did not pass
through the crystal
in special crystals called birefringent
crystals the phase change is actually
different in the horizontal and vertical
directions this means that a light wave
whose horizontal and vertical
polarizations are aligned before
entering the crystal can have a phase
Difference by the time they exit the
crystal
for example let's say we take a
birefringent crystal and aim a
diagonally polarized wave D towards it
where the horizontal and vertical
components are in phase
if the crystal introduces a quarter
cycle phase change and the vertical
component then the resulting wave is a
left circularly polarized wave l
this Crystal that changes the vertical
polarization by a quarter cycle is
called a quarter wave plate and it is
represented by this Matrix here
if we apply this Matrix to our
diagonally polarized Jones Vector it
leaves the horizontal polarization alone
but applies a quarter phase change to
the vertical polarization
remember the imaginary I is a quarter
turn around the complex unit circle so
it represents a phase change of a
quarter cycle
if we apply this quarter wave plate
again by multiplying by the same Matrix
it will cause the H and V polarizations
to realign again but with an opposite
sign in the v polarization which is the
same thing as a half cycle phase change
this gives the anti-diagonal
polarization a
applying the quarter wave plate again
the V polarization is changed yet again
to give negative I which is a
three-quarter cycle phase change which
gives a right circularly polarized wave
r
and applying the quarter wave plate
again brings us back to where we
originally started with the diagonal
polarization d
so this Matrix here allows us to rotate
around in a circle between these four
polarizations
dla and R and actually if we replace
this imaginary I which represents a
quarter phase with an arbitrary phase we
can rotate continuously around this
circle with any phase we like and this
gives us all sorts of different
polarizations including elliptical
polarizations
if we rotate around this circle the
polarizations look like this
now it's interesting to note that if we
put a horizontally polarized wave H
through this quarter wave plate nothing
actually happens the output wave is
still horizontally polarized but that
doesn't mean that this wave plate is
totally useless for horizontally
polarized waves
we can make something interesting happen
if we rotate this wave plate by 45
degrees in this case the output wave is
a left circularly polarized wave l
this isn't surprising if you think about
it because the setup we have here is the
exact same setup as our previous example
but with everything rotated in Space by
45 degrees
the physics is the same we're just
viewing it from a different angle
however when viewed from this angle our
quarter wave plate rotated by 45 degrees
is represented by this new Matrix
you'll notice that this Matrix contains
a phase Factor e to the I pi over 4
written in Gray we'll see later that we
can actually ignore this phase Factor
but for now I'm going to include it
you can think of this new Matrix as a
combination of three matrices
the first Matrix will rotate our
coordinates 45 degrees so that our
coordinate system is now aligned with
the main directions of the wave plate
then we apply the original quarter
waveplate Matrix we saw in our previous
example
then we rotate our coordinate system
back by 45 degrees in the opposite
direction
when we combine these three procedures
through matrix multiplication we get
this new Matrix which represents a
quarter wave plate angled at 45 degrees
as you can see it turns a horizontally
polarized wave into a left circularly
polarized wave
once again I'm ignoring this phase
Factor outside here and I'll explain why
in a moment
if we apply this wave plate multiple
times we get waves that are vertically
polarized right circularly polarized and
then we return to horizontally polarized
again
so this wave plate rotated by 45 degrees
represented by this Matrix takes us in a
circle around the polarizations
hlv and r
and again we can actually rotate
continuously along this circle to get
all sorts of polarizations in between we
just need to take our rotation matrices
from before and set them to an arbitrary
angle Theta instead of using 45 degrees
this corresponds to rotating our wave
plate by an arbitrary angle
now let's get back to all these phase
factors that I've been ignoring why is
it okay to ignore these phase factors
well we know that if we take a
diagonally polarized wave and shift the
vertical component of the wave by a
quarter phase we end up with a left
circularly polarized wave
but now instead let's shift both the
horizontal and vertical components by a
quarter phase
the result is just shifting the entire
Wave by a quarter phase the wave's
diagonal polarization is unchanged we've
just shifted the wave along the axis of
travel
so when it comes to using Jones vectors
to represent wave polarizations
multiplying both components of the Jones
vector by the same phase has no effect
on the wave's polarization all this does
is shift the wave along the axis of
travel
so when it comes to polarizations there
are multiple Jones vectors that
represent the same polarization each
with a different total phase factor in
front
so we can ignore these total phases when
studying wave polarizations because
total phase shifts don't change the
polarization of a wave
so we have this Matrix for rotating in a
circle between the polarizations D L A
and R and this Matrix rotates us in a
circle between the polarizations hlv and
r
putting these two circles together we
get a sort of sphere shape
this indicates that there should be
another Matrix for rotating between h a
v and d and that ends up being true
rotating between h a v and D is the same
thing as looking at the X Y plane and
rotating the wave clockwise which is
given by this Matrix here for quarter
turns and given by this Matrix here for
rotating continuously
so all together we see that we can
arrange all our polarizations of light
on a sphere like this this is called the
plank array sphere we initially
discovered these three matrices for
performing quarter turns on the sphere
and these matrices can be generalized to
continuous angles which allows us to
reach any point on the sphere giving any
arbitrary Jones Vector of amplitude 1.
so what's so special about these
matrices what do they have in common it
turns out that these matrices all belong
to a group of matrices called U2 the
unitary group of two by two matrices
but what does this mean
well the key idea for rotating across
this sphere is that we are not changing
the amplitudes of our waves
so we're just rotating the Jones vectors
on the sphere without changing their
lengths
so U2 matrices represent rotations on
the sphere of polarizations
to understand this let's go back to 3D
vectors for a moment one way to get the
squared length of a vector v is to treat
V as a column and write the squared
length as V transpose V where the
transpose operation just means we flip
columns into rows
when we perform this array
multiplication we get x squared plus y
squared plus Z squared which is the
standard Pythagoras formula for the
squared length of a 3D vector
now what if we wanted to apply a matrix
R to this Vector to rotate the vector
how do we determine what this Matrix R
would look like
well a key fact about rotating vectors
is that their length doesn't change
under rotation
so if we take our formula for the
squared length of v and then apply our
rotation Matrix R to V this should not
change the result of the original
squared length formula so these two
formulas must be equal
it's a standard rule from linear algebra
that the transpose of a product of
arrays is equal to the transposes of the
individual arrays multiplied in the
reverse order
so we can write RV all transposed as V
transpose R transpose
so this equation is telling us that if R
is a rotation Matrix that doesn't change
the length of vectors then R transpose R
must be equal to the identity Matrix
another way of saying this is that our
transpose is the inverse of r
if R is a three by three Matrix with the
columns highlighted like this then our
transpose involves flipping the columns
into rows to give us this
now remember R transpose multiplied by R
gives us the identity Matrix this gives
us some interesting relationships
between The Columns of r
notice that when we multiply any column
by its transpose we get one
this tells us that The Columns of R if
treated as vectors each have magnitude
one
also if we multiply any column by a
different columns transpose we get 0.
this tells us that The Columns of R if
treated as vectors are all orthogonal to
each other
matrices that satisfy these properties
are called orthogonal matrices and we
write the group of all orthogonal three
by three matrices as O3
so we know our rotations in 3D are done
by O3 matrices but we've actually missed
an important detail it's true that
rotations don't change the length of a
vector but Reflections also don't change
the length of a vector so this O3 group
of matrices that don't change Vector
lengths contains both rotation matrices
and reflection matrices
if we take the formula R transpose R
equals the identity and take the
determinant of both sides we know from
linear algebra that the determinant of a
product equals the product of the
determinants
and also taking the transpose of a
matrix doesn't affect the determinant so
we ignore the transpose
since the determinant of the identity
Matrix is one this tells us that the
determinant of R is either plus one or
minus 1.
remember the determinant of a matrix
tells us how much it changes the areas
of squares in two Dimensions or the
volumes of cubes in three dimensions
rotations have a determinant of plus one
since rotations don't change areas or
volumes
Reflections don't change the size of
volumes but Reflections reverse
directions and this results in a
determinant of minus one
so if we only want to look at matrices
that do rotations and not Reflections we
have to only look at the orthogonal
matrices with determinant plus one this
is called the special orthogonal group
SO3 where the word special means we're
restricting ourselves to matrices with a
determinant of plus one
so we know that the special orthogonal
3x3 matrices will perform rotations on
3D vectors without changing their
lengths
now getting back to our sphere of
polarizations we want to know what kind
of matrices will rotate our Jones
vectors around without changing their
amplitudes
this sounds similar to rotating 3D
vectors but there's one key difference
Jones vectors have complex number
entries instead of real number entries
if we have the complex number C equals
three plus four I we don't get its
squared magnitude by doing c times c as
this gives us another complex number and
magnitudes must be real
instead the squared magnitude is given
by c times the complex conjugate of CE
which is denoted with this star and
flips the sign of the imaginary part
this results in the correct magnitude of
C which is the real number five
so when we want the squared magnitude of
a complex Jones Vector J it's not enough
to write J transpose J as this might
give us a complex number result
instead we write J transpose complex
conjugate times J to get the correct
squared magnitude
this combination of transpose and
complex conjugate is called the
hermitian conjugate and is usually
written with a single dagger symbol
so to get to the squared magnitude of a
Jones Vector we use J dagger J
as an exercise you can check that each
of these Jones vectors indeed has a
magnitude of one
so if we rotate a Jones Vector J around
with a matrix U the result of the
magnitude formula should stay the same
so these two formulas are equal
rewriting u j all daggered as J dagger
you dagger we see that our rotation
Matrix U must obey U dagger U equals the
identity in other words U inverse equals
its complex conjugate transpose
we call matrices with this property
unitary they are sort of like the
complex number equivalent of orthogonal
matrices since they rotate complex
vectors around without changing their
magnitude
the group of two by two unitary matrices
is called U2 and another good exercise
to try is to pause the video and confirm
you can get to the inverse of all of
these matrices by taking their complex
transpose
taking the determinant of this formula
for U2 matrices we get that the squared
magnitude of the determinant must be one
but since the determinant of U is a
complex number the answer isn't just
plus or minus one instead the answer can
be any complex number on the unit circle
with magnitude one and this can be
written in the form of e to the I times
Theta
we can check its magnitude is 1 by
multiplying it by its complex conjugate
and canceling the exponents
so we know that U2 matrices can rotate
our Jones vectors on the point array
sphere but once again there's something
we've missed recall that any two Jones
vectors that are the same but with a
different phase factor in front
represents the same polarization
for example each of these Jones vectors
represents a left circularly polarized
wave
this means that if we want to turn a
diagonally polarized wave into a left
circularly polarized wave there are
multiple U2 matrices that can do this
all identical but with a different phase
factor in front because we can ignore
the phase factor and the final result
anyway
so the group of U2 matrices has some
redundancy given by this phase factor
out in front
however it's possible to pick out a
unique U2 Matrix that takes us between a
specific initial and a specific final
polarization all we need to do is to
find the specific U2 Matrix that has a
determinant of plus one
so if we have some U2 Matrix with a
determinant that's equal to a complex
number e to the I Theta we can convert
it into an equivalent Matrix with a
determinant of plus one by following the
below procedure
we just multiply all the elements of the
matrix by e to the negative I Theta over
two
after taking the determinant combining
the exponents and factoring these
exponentials cancel and we get a
determinant of plus one
this multiplicative phase Factor doesn't
affect the polarization of our Jones
vectors since we can ignore overall
phase factors anyway
the set of two by two unitary matrices
with a determinant equal to plus one is
called su2 the special unitary group of
two by two matrices this is the set of
matrices that rotate our Jones vectors
around on this sphere of polarizations
again the word special means the
matrices that have a determinant of plus
one
we'll finish this video by explaining
why these Jones vectors are considered
spinners
notice that in physical space vertical
and horizontal polarizations are angled
90 degrees apart but on the sphere of
polarizations we've created the hnv
polarizations are on opposite sides 180
degrees apart
so a quarter turn in physical space
corresponds to a half turn in
polarization space
if we do another quarter turn in
physical space we end up at the negative
vertical polarization where the negative
sign indicates the wave has an extra
phase of half a cycle compared to the
starting wave
but in polarization space we've done
another half turn and completed a full
loop and are back to where we started
when it comes to polarizations there is
no difference between a vertical
polarization with a positive sign in
front and a vertical polarization with a
negative sign in front
the overall phase shift doesn't matter
and both are considered vertical
polarizations
since wave polarizations are unchanged
by an overall phase shift the Jones
vectors in our polarization space are
unable to see the negative sign in front
of the wave
all it sees is a vertically polarized
wave
to get back to the original wave we do
another half turn in physical space
which corresponds to another full turn
in the polarization space
so a full turn in physical space
requires two full turns in polarization
space
this is why Jones vectors are considered
Spinners rotating a wave back to its
original state requires two full
rotations of the Jones Vector in
polarization space
so when we rotate by an angle Theta in
polarization space this corresponds to a
rotation by an angle of theta over 2 in
physical space
for this reason you will often see the
su2 matrices that are used to rotate
Jones vectors written with half angles
like this because when we want to rotate
by an angle of Pi in polarization space
this corresponds to rotating our Jones
Vector components by an angle of pi over
2.
this is how we get from the V
polarization to the H polarization
in the next video we're going to learn
about Quantum spin States and how they
are also described by Spinners that
transform with su2 matrices even though
this is a different physical phenomenon
we'll find that the mathematics of
analyzing Quantum spin States is almost
the exact same as the math required for
analyzing polarizations of light waves
this will show us that Spinners are
indeed useful tools that can solve
multiple problems
if you're interested in doing one last
exercise you can try rotating this Jones
Vector around this path using these
matrices and checking if the final
result makes sense